<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Michele's web</title>
 <link href="http://michelemattioni.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://michelemattioni.me"/>
 <updated>2012-06-05T00:01:51+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://michelemattioni.me</id>
 <author>
   <name>Michele Mattioni</name>
   <email>mattions@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>NeuroML and standards</title>
   <link href="http://michelemattioni.me/acedemic/2012/06/04/neuroml-and-standards"/>
   <updated>2012-06-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://michelemattioni.me/acedemic/2012/06/04/neuroml-and-standards</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;img src='/assets/gfx/NeuroML_logo.png' /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing complex models (like mine) is only possible if we can reuse and merge smaller models. To achieve this we need a system to archive and express models in standard way that is no tight to one specific software, it represents the model in a not ambigous way, and it&amp;#8217;s available to everybody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of having a lego system, where we can plug different models together is very appealing in computational neuroscience, and it will give the possibility to simulate more complex scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In systems biology &lt;a href='http://sbml.org/'&gt;SBML&lt;/a&gt; is definitively one of the leader of this effort. In computational neuroscience a complementary effort is &lt;a href='http://neuroml.org'&gt;NeuroML&lt;/a&gt;. Version 2.0 is under construction; to contribute or check it out go to the &lt;a href='https://github.com/NeuralEnsemble/libNeuroML'&gt;NeuralEnsemble/libNeuroml repo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Multiscale modelling, integrating electrical and biochemical</title>
   <link href="http://michelemattioni.me/academic/2012/06/04/multiscale-modelling"/>
   <updated>2012-06-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://michelemattioni.me/academic/2012/06/04/multiscale-modelling</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src='/assets/gfx/spines_detailed_thumbnail.png' /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A model can be considered multiscale when one or both these conditions are true: (i) the object of the modelling spawns different orders of magnitude in at least time or space e.g.: from microseconds (μs) to minutes (min), or from nanometers (nm) to millimeters (mm); (ii) parts of the model run with different timescales and/or with different spatial resolutions, influencing each other through a systematic exchange of variables (Weinan and Engquist, 2003).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of the simulation is the summa of the different approaches, combined together, and cannot be achieved using one part of the model only, or simulating them in a disconnected way. All branches of Biology are inherently multiscale. Neuroscience as well has also to address multiscale problems, where for example, an excitatory release of glutamate can trigger an increase in the Calcium concentration, which can then act as second messenger, stimulating complex biochemical cascades with timescales spanning from minutes to hours or days. Nonetheless, given the wide spectrum of the processes involved, communities have focused on one particular domain, the electrical aspect or the biochemical one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my Ph.D. I have developed an event-driven algorithm which allows to integrate different simulators, optimizing the number of syncs between the two and the time of the syncing. At the same time I&amp;#8217;ve also developed a multiscale model of a Medium Spiny Neuron of the Striatum, with 1504 spine modelled explicitely where the plasticity, the strenght of a synapse, is computed as the results of the integration between the electrical and the biochemical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src='/assets/gfx/multiscale_simulation_msn.png' /&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Neuronvisio, a Neuron companion</title>
   <link href="http://michelemattioni.me/academic/2012/06/01/neuronvisio"/>
   <updated>2012-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://michelemattioni.me/academic/2012/06/01/neuronvisio</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;img src='/assets/gfx/pyramidal_3D_change_voltage.png' /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuronvisio is a Graphical User Interface for NEURON simulator environment with 3D capabilities. Neuronvisio makes easy to select and investigate sections’ properties and it offers easy integration with matplotlib for plotting the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The geometry can be saved using NeuroML and the computational results in a customised and extensible HDF5 format; the results can then be reload in the software and analysed in a later stage, without re-running the simulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='features'&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3D visualization of the model with the possibility to change it runtime&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Creation of vectors to record any variables present in the section&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Pylab integration to plot directly the result of the simulation&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Exploration of the timecourse of any variable among time using a color coded scale&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Saving the results simulation for later analysis&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Automatic download and running of models in ModelDB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More info at &lt;a href='http://neuronvisio.org'&gt;http://neuronvisio.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>